[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net. SE Radio is brought to you
by the ITE computer society and by it e
software magazine online at
computer.org/software. Hello, this is
Srian Piam for software engineering
radio. Today I have with me Ken Gross,
the creator of HTMX, a library that's
challenging how we thinking about modern
web development and by returning to the
hypermediadriven principles of the early
web and all the while delivering modern
user experiences. Welcome to the show,
Carson. Thank you. Very excited to be
here. It's uh really nice to be able to
talk on a show that's a little bit more
geared towards software engineering and
sort of like principles instead of just
like here's another you know here's how
HTMX works. So I'm excited I'm excited
to talk about sort of the philosophy and
software engineering around it. Sounds
great. Before we dive into the details
of HTMX, I want to get your perspective
on the current state of web development.
These days web development seems to
involve a lot of complexity. you know,
complex tooling, complex frameworks.
Could you share your perspective on
where it's at? Yeah, I agree with that.
I think obviously I wouldn't have
created HTMX, which we'll get into the
details of exactly how it works later,
but it is a simpler I think way of
creating at least a certain class or a
certain percentage of web applications.
And I think as you point out in the last
say 10 15 years, web development has
gotten pretty complicated. Part of that
was driven by needs. Obviously, if you
need a more sophisticated user
interface, things get more complicated.
But I think part of it too was just
driven by developers. We have a hard
time saying no to things and, you know,
the shiny new thing and being impressed
by sophisticated approaches rather than
maybe accepting a little bit less sizzle
but with a simpler approach. And so, I
think it's been a mix of those things. I
don't think I'm alone in suggesting in
modern web development, which is really
I think the main area HTMX is
interesting, is pretty complicated now.
There are a lot of people that are very
good at it and experts at it. So, and I
don't want to denigrate what they can do
and what they can achieve with the tools
they have, but at the same time, I do
think there's a, like I said, a large
class of web applications in particular
that could be simplified using some of
these older ideas. Nice. And in terms of
these challenges, where and how does a
hypermediadriven approach come in? I
mean, first of all, what is it? Yeah,
let's talk about what the hypermedia
approach is. So, HTMX is what I call a
hypermediadriven library. And what that
means is that it uses the ideas of
hypermedia, which are very old. I mean,
the term was coined back in the 1960s.
And obviously, the web was invented in
the 1990s, so you're talking about some
pretty old ideas at this point. But with
HTMX, the idea is let's take those ideas
and sort of extend them. And really the
big idea I would say in hyperdia is this
notion of what's called a hypermedia
control. What makes hyperdia interesting
from a technical standpoint is that you
mix control information and display
information in a single document. And I
don't know if you know like Ted Nelson
might not wouldn't probably talk about
it in that way, but I'm taking my
terminology from Roy Fielding's
dissertation. He had a famous
dissertation about rest was describing
the web and I've written a paper an ACM
paper that you can read called
generalizing hyperdia controls that sort
of riffs on this idea. But again to get
back to your original question a
hypermedia is a media so some format
that sort of display content like we're
used to when we talk about media but
then it has these special things called
hypermedia controls mixed in. And so the
canonical hypermedia control is the
anchor tag. And so you put an anchor tag
in an HTML document and then someone
clicks on it and they go somewhere else.
That doesn't seem like much probably to
you or me because we're so used to the
web. But from a historical perspective,
what you're doing is you're putting
control information in the document.
You're putting navigation in the
document itself. And that's really what
makes it a hyperdia, something that's
beyond normal media. So when the term
hypermedia was coined, Nelson was
contrasting it with like books and you
know magazines and and things like this
where he just kind of plotted through it
directly and I I think the informal
definition that he gave was basically
any sort of media that needs to be
consumed on a computer because computers
allow you to have these interactive
experiences. So again I from my
perspective as a computer scientist like
I really focus in on this notion of
hypermedia controls. We've talked about
links. The other major hypermedia
control that's available in HTML, which
is a hypermedia format, is our forms.
And so if your listeners have ever
created a form in HTML to submit, you
know, a contact or something like that
or just filled out like everyone has
experience with a credit card form at
this point and click submit and then you
purchase something. That's different.
that actually forms were added in HTML 2
and it was really a pretty massive and
step forward in the ideas of hypermedia
which hasn't been discussed a whole
bunch because hyperdia before that
wasn't always but it it didn't have this
explicit notion of reading and writing.
So hypermedia before the form tag again
there was a bunch of different
hypermedia systems so I don't want to
say universally but it was very tightly
associated with the notion of navigation
like clicking hyperlinks but when forms
came along in HTML 2 that really
transformed the web as a hypermedia
system as a system built on top of
hyperdia from a readonly system which is
what it was initially designed as a way
to share research documents at CERN into
a potential web application like a
potential application mechanism. And so
we sort of stumbled around for the next
10 to 15 years figuring out, okay, how
are we going to build web apps and model
view controller? How does that apply to
the web? And so on and so forth. So I
think if someone's like, okay, what is a
hypermedia? What I'm going to tell them,
the one-s sentence answer is it's a
media, something that displays media in
some way that also allows you to encode
actions in or control actions via
hypermedia controls in it. Interesting.
Interesting. So, and that's sort of what
the web was. So, sorry I got off on a
tangent there, but that was the history
of the web. And then what HTMX does is
takes those ideas and sort of extends
them. So, that's pretty good context.
How does that either relate or conflict
with the restful approaches that you
know Royy's dissertation brought us 20
years ago? Yeah. So I think what you're
referring to is Roy Fielding's famous
dissertation at the University of Irvine
which gave us the term in chapter five
of that dissertation gave us the term
rest which stands for representational
state transfer and that document it
takes a a network perspective like a
network architecture perspective and
defines the restful network architecture
in terms of a series of constraints. I
have to say I don't think there was as
much focus in there. Well, I mean it was
his dissertation. He was concerned about
network architecture just not his real
thing. But I focus much more on
hypermedia controls as the interesting
part of it. And so basically in that
dissertation he gave like there's a
series of five constraints I think and a
sixth optional one that define whether
or not a system is restful. The most
important of those constraints on a
network architecture I think is what's
called the uniform interface constraint.
And that is it's the last one before the
optional scripting constraint. Basically
what he noted about hypermedia, one
thing that's interesting about it is
because you encode the control actions
directly in the media that are returned
from the server. It has this very unique
characteristic as a just a way to build
distributed systems in that clients and
here client means browsers don't need to
know in advance how a website works.
Instead, they enter the website through
a URL and then as you interact with that
website, all of the actions that you
take are discovered through the HTML or
the hyper media is what I would say that
is returned from that system. And so
that's called a uniform interface
because the client, the browser in this
case, can interact with any website
regardless of its domain. So if the
website is a car sales website or if
it's a hospital or bank or if it's a
coffee shop or whatever, the browser
doesn't know any of those concepts. It
doesn't know what a coffee shop is or
anything like that. And the network
communications with that system are all
done in terms of hypermedia. So this
browser has this kind of crazy
characteristic to it where it's a
universal client because there's this
hypermedia that provides with a uniform
interface to access that system. And
another aspect of this that I think is
sometimes overlooked with this uniform
interface of hypermedia is that you can
dramatically change a website and if I
go to it, I don't need to update my app
to use it. I don't have to update to
like the current version of the API.
Instead, your website or web
application, however you want to think
about it, just returns here are the
current things you can do. And then I
select the actions from those responses.
And so the restful approach that that
Fielding was pointing out has this
really nice characteristic where if
you're doing it properly then you don't
have to worry about versioning your
network API as much because just this
nice characteristic of the uniform
interface of hypermedia. It's kind of
ironic. I I don't know if you've read I
have an essay on the HTMX website called
how did REST come to mean the opposite
of REST? because today if people use the
term rest they're typically talking
about JSON format APIs and those are
actually they're very unrestful for the
most part and I don't mean that in a
moral sense I'm not saying they're bad
for not being restful but they're just
from a descriptive standpoint they're
not if you take the original definition
of that seriously mainly because they
don't communicate in terms of a
hypermedia which has this uniform
interface aspect to it. So it's an
interesting if your listeners are
interested they can go read that essay
on the
htmx.org/sayas website. It's called how
did rest come to me in the opposite of
rest. In a way I mean what I'm hearing
is with hypermedia it's kind of
userentric in that the user the client
will come in there and do things on that
site or on that application without
necessarily knowing or needing to care
about the modeling of those things
behind it. Right. Which sounds like what
rest might be more focused on. Yeah,
that's exactly right. Unfortunately, I
find it's often difficult to communicate
that properly to people because
particularly when you're today we've
specialized in many ways into sort of
front end and back end. And so the front
end people think in terms of libraries
like React and so forth and the backend
people think in terms of what they
consider an API and what they consider
an API is typically what I would call a
data API, an RPC style data API. maybe
not RPC, there's restful aspects to it,
but at the end of the day, they're not
returning hyperdia. And when you
suggest, hey, here's this other
approach. They often like are
flabbergasted and say like, that's a
horrible API because it's my UI. I'm
coupling my API to my UI. And they're
right. I mean, they're not wrong. Like
the end of the day, when you're
returning Hypermedia, at some level,
you're returning the UI. So, what I
would say about that is it's coupled at
the application level. Now on the other
hand, I think one thing that's
interesting to think about is this fact
that the browser doesn't need to be
updated when you change your website if
you use hyper media. And so whereas if
you're using a JSON API and you have an
SPA or something like that, then you do
have to or maybe to make it even more
explicit like a mobile client, you know,
a thick application that's talking to a
JSON API. If you change your JSON API,
you have to change your client too. And
so at some level those two things are
actually more tightly coupled. Coupled.
Yep. They're more tightly coupled than
the pure web application is. I think I I
don't want to put words into his mouth,
but the way I interpret fieldings, the
way Fielding talks about this stuff and
certainly the way I think about it is
that what is happening there is that
REST decouples client and server at the
network architecture level, not at the
application level. And so you couple
yourself more tightly at the application
level, but by doing that you actually
decouple lower down. And so you get this
nice characteristic where if you change
what your endpoints return then to a
first order approximation anyways, you
don't have to update the client, the
client being the browser in any major
way. I think that's an interesting sort
of you know for the listeners of this
podcast that are interested in software
engineering I think that's an
interesting thing to think about because
it appears that there are different
meanings of coupling and the fact that
when you change a JSON API you have to
change the client even though the JSON
API feels more generic at some level
implies there's some coupling going on
there right that's sort of the
definition thereof and so I think it's
something that software engineers should
think about because it's it's just an
interesting characterist istic of rest,
right? No, that helps with the context
of HTMX, right? I mean, so how does HTMX
take this and extend it and what was the
origin story of this, right? Origin
story is actually very practical. I was
trying to sort a table and and I was
doing it in like 2010, so a long time
ago. And I was doing it in JavaScript on
the client side because that's what all
the cool kids were doing at that point.
and I was using jQuery and I was just
having a bear of a time making it go
fast enough and I just couldn't you know
on the browsers of the time which didn't
have the highly optimized JavaScript
runtimes that we have today it wouldn't
sort quickly enough and so out of
desperation I tried this trick that
jQuery had a method I think called load
I think on jQuery so if you're an old
jQuery person you can look that up and
what that does is it takes a URL and
then puts the result into an element in
the DOM like just issues an HTTP get
request and then puts it into the DOM.
So I tried that again just sort of out
of desperation and lo and behold it was
like instant. I could sort it really
quickly and I think that was an artifact
of the JavaScript runtimes of the time.
You know everything was kind of bad this
you know way back in the day but I found
out you could do that and was like oh
this is cool. And so I started building
up some tools around that method and
then I saw I don't know how familiar
your listeners are with web development
but Angular one when Angular one came
out they used attributes in HTML to
drive behavior and I didn't like the way
that they were doing it but I like that
idea of like let's use attributes that
because you know oh okay I have an href
and an anchor tag and now I've got my
own little thing that does something
different. And so I started mixing sort
of these ideas together into a helper
library that I was using. And then I
eventually released that helper library
as a library called intercooler.js. And
that was in 2013 is when I finally
released it. And when I did that, I
started getting people emailing me and
saying, "Hey, this is cool. This is
Restful." And at the time, I didn't
understand rest like nowhere near as
well as I understand. I hope anyways as
I understand it now. But I went back and
I'd read Fielding's thesis but not you
know that much and I didn't understand a
lot of it. I didn't understand what the
uniform interface was. But I slowly over
time recognized oh okay this library is
actually it's restful. It's actually and
I would go further and say it's
hypermedia oriented like that's what
makes this library distinct from other
options like say you know react or
angular was the big thing at the time or
whatever. And so what I came to
understand and if you go to the HTMX or
website you can see sort of like in the
introduction what I came to understand
is that an HTMX I'm sorry I should just
mention HTMX is a rewrite of jQuery or
excuse me of intercooler because
intercoolerjs depended on jQuery. So
htmx is a standalone library. It doesn't
depend on jQuery because the JavaScript
runtimes have come so far. But if you go
to htmx.org And you look at the
introduction, there's sort of a
motivation part of it. And the idea here
is so if you think about hyperdia in
terms of hyperdia controls, we really
only have two that we can build things
with, right? So links and forms. I think
it's a testament to how powerful
hyperdia is that we could build so much
of the web with just those two things.
You know, the first 15 years of the web,
that was pretty much it. there was some
JavaScript, you know, coming along and
we built quite a bit of useful
functionality with just those two
hypermedia controls. And so what HTMX
says is, okay, why should only anchor
tags and forms be able to issue HTTP
requests? There are two elements, but
what makes them special? There are other
elements that you might want to issue a
request based on. For example, a button
is an obvious one. Like why can't
buttons issue requests? Also right now
the way the HTML specification works you
can only issue what are called get and
post style methods and so HTTP itself
the protocol actually supports
additional HTTP methods. So there's like
a delete request and there's a put and a
patch or there you have these other
options. And so HTMX says okay not only
can anything make a request but also
they can make any of these types of
requests. And then finally, the sort of
like last big piece of the puzzle is why
should when you submit a request, why
should you have to replace the entire
viewport? So why not make it so that
rather than replacing the entire
viewport, we can just replace some chunk
of the current document. That's actually
not a new idea. That's called
transclusion. It's been around for a
long time. So there's a lot of academic
work in the hypermedia world around that
notion. and it actually exists in HTML
believe it or not. So there is an
attribute on links and forms called
target and you can use that attribute to
target an I frame and only an I frame
which is interesting but it really it
makes it a limiting a pretty limiting
thing in the overall scheme of things
because iframes for better or for worse
have just kind of they have this
historical baggage associated with them.
And so what HTMX says is okay anything
can issue an HTTP request. It can be any
kind of HTTP request. And then in
addition, the hypermedia that comes back
and this is a big distinction between
HTMX and say React is HTMX expects HTML
to come back from the server. That HTML
can be placed anywhere in the DOM. And
so there's a couple of ways you can
specify exactly how that happens. Oh,
and you know, and excuse me, I I missed
one other concept earlier. There's also
the notion of the event that triggers
the request. M. So when you're talking
about anchor tags or links, a click
triggers that interaction. And when
you're talking about forms, a submit
action triggers that. Well, there's a
bunch of other actions or events that
occur in an application that you might
want to have some interaction with the
server. And so HTMX also makes it
possible for any action to trigger a
request. And so that ends up being the
sort of four generalizations of HTML
that I talk about. So any element can
issue any type of request in response to
any event and it can place the response
content anywhere in the DOM. And so I
know this might come across as arrogant
but I like to say it completes HTML as a
hypermedia and that it sort of fully
generalizes this notion that I think is
super important of hypermedia controls
in HTML. So that's the sort of
philosophical basis of HTMX. Great.
Again, you know, our listeners are quite
familiar with frameworks like React and
Vue and, you know, so-called modern
frameworks, right? Now, obviously,
there's a serverside focus to HTMX and
there's a large client side focus to
these frameworks. But beyond that, at a
more deeper level, you know, where do
you see the diversions? Where do you see
the compatibilities? Where do you see
the, you know, yeah, I think the big
thing is really hyperdia. You know, I'll
keep saying it and that's one again
reason I've really focused on it. Like
my essays page, I have a lot and I've
said this on other podcasts. I think the
essays page is probably more important
than HTMX as a library in the long run
because just because it's got a lot of
ideas around hyperdia and it really is a
different way of building web
applications as Fielding noted in his
dissertation. It's a different way of
building applications. The hypermedia
systems work differently than
non-hypermedia systems. And I would say
a lot of the web applications that are
being built today use thick JavaScript
style, you know, talking to a JSON API.
It's funny that some of those actually
are more like the 1980s thick apps that
we did, right? Like JSON is the new
Corba or whatever is the new data
exchange standard that we have. And it
yeah, it's very loose and whatever, but
the way those applications work with the
back end is much more like a thick
application from the 1980s than it is
like a web application from say the
1990s or early 2000s, the sort of
traditional web application. You know,
again, I don't want to criticize people
for going down that when it first
happened. It was because the hypermedia
approach with only links and forms had a
lot of usability issues. I don't know if
you remember like old online email
clients where every time you clicked a
button it was a full page refresh and it
was you had to wait and like a little
dinosaur came out and like did a
cartwheel around a star or something
like that and you know it was charming
in its own way but does not have the
sophisticated feel of a modern
application to it. Yeah. Yeah. So people
very reasonably said okay well
JavaScript is here and then JSON and and
Ajax the technologies that sort of like
form the basis of a lot of applications
today came along and they said okay now
we can achieve better usability we don't
have to have this big you know kachchunk
or whatever every time I I want to do an
action so that was reasonable but when
that happened we also and I think at
some level inadvertently sort of left
behind the advantages of the hypermedia
approach because it just we're going
back to more like thick style apps. And
so HTMX, what it does is for a certain
class of web applications, it allows you
to achieve a better user experience
while still staying in that original
hypermedia model. And so it's not a good
answer for all applications because
hyperdia isn't a good answer for all
applications. But I think it does
significantly increase the number of web
applications that could be built using
the hypermedia approach. So, and I also
also just like as an aside, I think the
hypermedia approach is interesting
technically. So, even if you're not sold
on HTMX, just understanding the
engineering aspects, particularly the
uniform interface and this idea of
decoupling at different levels, I think
is worthwhile for web developers. Right.
Before I dive into the well, more of the
internals, I mean, something I wanted to
ask later, I I can ask that now. When
will HTMX not be suitable or not be the
most ideal choice for you? Yeah, I've
got an essay up called when to use
hypermedia, I believe, where I go over
some, you know, when is it a good idea,
when is it a bad idea, but basically if
you have interactions that drive a lot
of requests, like really fiddly
interactions. So, an example application
is like Google Maps where dragging a
mouse implies a bunch of UI updates.
That's something that you don't want
network latency to be hitting every time
someone moves a mouse. That's just not a
good user experience. And so that's
probably something that wouldn't be a
good application to address with HTMX. I
do think you could maybe do the settings
page for a map application in HTMX where
it's just a more traditional here's a
bunch of toggles and inputs or whatever
and then the user fills them out and
clicks save. that could be done very
effectively and that's sort of like in
my mind the ideal application for HTMX
is a sort of form driven applications
because there's a lot of think time and
the user interacts with things for a
while like interacts with local controls
for a little bit and then click save and
they're okay because they've done a
bunch of work so they they almost feel
better if it's not instant. I don't know
about you and your listeners but I'm not
a big fan of settings pages where
there's no save button where it's like
you just set it and then did it save,
did it change? Like am I good? do I
leave? Like what's going on? That's an
example where it's not even necessarily
like application versus application. It
could be as simple as just what's the
feature I'm currently working on where
you might choose hypermedia over a more
sophisticated approach like client
approach. Sounds good. Sounds good. I
was thinking more about the HTMX
attribute set, right? To help control a
lot of the client side behavior and
interactions. But there's also a big
focus or big advantage of using HTMX
from the server side perspective from
the backend perspective. Can you talk
about how you know HTMX integrates with
the server side of the application
development pipeline? Yeah. So one thing
that's different about HTMX is that it
puts a tremendous amount of focus on the
backend because the backend is producing
the UIs for your web application. Now
the backend becomes a much more
sophisticated a much more integral
component to your application. you
shrink down the amount of code that's in
the front end and that code tends to be
in HTML which you know you don't write
and again I'm sorry to jump around a
little bit here but in HTMX you don't
write JavaScript for the most part on
the front end when you're just using the
straight HTMX functionality you're
typically just putting attributes on
HTML to say okay this button issues a
request to this URL and then takes the
result and puts it in this place in the
DOM simple things like that and so what
that does is it puts a lot more logic on
the back end. In particular, you know,
if you're familiar with older web
development, you go back to templating
or some sort of HTML building tool
technology. Your front end gets built on
the back end. And because of that, what
that means is that a lot more of your
code is going to be written in whatever
back-end language you're using for that
system. So if you are a Go programmer,
then rather than having a large
JavaScript application that talks to a,
you know, maybe medium-sized Go
application, what you're gonna have
instead is a large Go application that
uses maybe Go templates or something
like Temple or something like that to
produce HTML and then everything kind of
lives on the back end or it feels much
more backend focused. And I think that's
a good thing for the following reason in
particular. First of all, let's say a
couple reasons. First of all, if you're
a Go programmer, switching back and
forth between Go and JavaScript probably
isn't something you want to do a ton of.
You're going to have to do a little bit
of it, but HTMX will help minimize that.
So, you can really focus in on the back
end in a much more focused manner. And
the other thing about it is that because
you don't have a large JavaScript
application on the front end, something
that you've seen in the last 10 years is
tremendous pressure to adopt JavaScript
on the back end because then you're
using one language. Why would we have if
we've got a big JavaScript system on the
front end, why would we have like Go or
you know whatever on the back end? So if
you use HTMX, it takes that pressure off
because you don't have a big JavaScript
on the front end. What that does is it
opens up the potential backends I think
in a way that if you adopt a large
JavaScript framework for your front end,
you're going to feel this pressure like
why aren't we using JavaScript or at
least TypeScript on the back end. And
with HTMX, you don't have that pressure.
And I like that because I teach the
compilers class at Montana State and I
like programming languages and I like
lots of different programming languages
and the cultures that grow up around
them. I felt like it would be a shame if
the JavaScript juggernaut kind of
steamrolled all these other languages
just by being having the advantage of
being there on the browser side. And so
I think HTMX helps address that and can
help people if they want to use a
particular programming language, you
know, they can use it on the server
side. it does push a lot of problems
that you have on the front end to the
back end. So how do we compose UIs? For
example, a lot of people who are used to
react or used to react components. So
the way you can address that is via UI
reuse on the back end which if in a
traditional templating system that might
be in template inclusion but they're
backend component systems that are
growing up as well. So it just it shifts
your problems to the back end which I
think is a good thing. everything else
being equal, it's better to have your
problems in one place rather than two
places. But that's maybe a subjective
claim. Fair enough. I mean, I certainly
have felt this problem where there's a
pressure to kind of use the one language
that's decided by what's in your front
end, right? And it can get a bit
uncomfortable, right? One thing here in
this pattern, how would this differ from
the BFF pattern, like the back end for
front end pattern? Could you give me a
quick over? So, I've heard BFF before
and people have come at me with the term
before. Could you give me a quick
overview of it so I can figure I just
want to make sure I don't I feel like I
understand what it is but I don't want
to I don't want to speak incorrectly if
I have a bad understanding. My
understanding my limit my limited
understanding is that just like you
would have your data layer and your
application UI layer. You might have a
layer or an API that determines what the
UI model should look like. If a forms
page needs a object list three four
entities it'll be the collecting layer
for the front end. Right. Okay. Yeah. My
understanding of it, again, I'll just
lay out if I'm addressing the wrong
thing, I apologize, but this is what I'm
going to try to address. My
understanding of backend for front end
is the idea that there's back-end code
that is tied to your front-end needs in
the form of objects that maybe model it.
And then also, you see this idea that
you should split your application API
and your pure data API up, right? They
should be two different endpoints. So
like general purpose people who want to
consume you know a general purpose data
API have one set of endpoints and then
your application has another set of
endpoints and I think HTMX speaks to
that in the following way. First of all
I agree that you should have your web
application API and your JSON your data
API split up into two separate
components. And I would say further if
it makes sense that your application API
should maybe be in terms of hypermedia
using something like HTMX because
hypermedia makes a bad generalpurpose
data API. You don't want to be pulling
down HTML from some website and like
trying to figure out what the HTML is.
That's just not what it's designed for.
M so I think the reason you see people
advocate for this split though in the
JSON world even if you have JSON APIs
there's this pressure for this split
between what my application's doing and
what the general purpose data API is. I
assert that that is there because
there's a fundamental tension between
your application needs and the needs of
general purpose data API. So general
purpose data API needs to be stable
number one, right? Because people use it
and so that's why they're typically
versioned and so forth. So it needs to
be stable. It needs to be general. It
needs to provide general data access to
like whatever possible reasonable needs
might occur. It also needs to have
things like rate limiting. You know, you
don't want to let someone just hammer on
your data API and so forth. On the other
hand, the application API tends to be
much more churny because your front end
changes so dramatically and so quickly.
And furthermore, you have specific needs
for a particular UI and implementing the
fetches against a general purpose data
API that might be necessary to get that
data could be really expensive when
instead what you could do is on the back
end sort of collect everything that you
need for the UI and just send it back in
one chunk. But you don't want to do that
in your general purpose API because now
it's not general purpose. It's for a
particular UI. So I think what you're
seeing there is this tension between the
need for a general purpose API and the
need to respond quickly and have very
efficient queries for your UI needs. And
I assert that in many of those cases if
you can get the interactivity that you
need out of it anyways using hypermedia
for your application API rather than
JSON will give you even more advantages
because then you know with hypermedia
you sort of have the ideal interaction
with the server in that you issue one
request and you get back the entire UI
and that's it. So you don't have these
like chatty interactions where you're
you know hitting a bunch of different
endpoints to wire together all the data
that's necessary. You also send the
ideal amount of data on the response
because you're sending the UI. You don't
send any extraneous data. And so if
you're using a general purpose data API,
very often you're getting back data that
you don't care about. Like you just need
maybe a couple fields to build that UI.
And so I think from what I understand of
it, the back end for front end idea is
sound. I just would add and by the way
the front end might be hyperdia. And if
you do that, to me as an old school guy,
I would think of it more as model view
controller. That's just maybe I just
grew up on it. Mhm. I would just think
you want to have two different
controllers and then they talk to a
model that represents your domain model
and your data API which won't change
very much because you've taken the
application churniness out of it can
just work against a very generic you
know modeled you know return table just
return things as JSON JSON serialization
is pretty simple and then your
application controllers can be tuned and
they can change a whole bunch as you
change your UI because it's a hypermedia
API so you're not trying to satisfy two
sets of people with it. You're just this
is for your web app. And so I think it's
a good fit philosophically for that
problem. I don't know again the details
of back end for front end I'm not super
familiar with, but to me it feels like a
good fit for certain types of
applications facing that. No, you you
touched upon it pretty pretty well. You
talked about churnney applications and
that obviously brings us to managing
state, right? Obviously in client side
heavy applications, state's kind of
somewhat simpler to manage in one place.
So this shift in burden, how does that
change? How does that make it easier or
harder? And what are the performance
characteristics of this? I would take
issue with the idea that it's simpler.
It's a local cache, right? It depends on
the application of course, but for most
web applications, what you have if
you're in an SPA and you or a single
page application, a JavaScript heavy
application, you have a local cache of
what the data on the server looks like.
And your listeners are probably familiar
with the adage that there's only two
hard problems in computer science,
right? like naming and cache
invalidation and off by one errors. And
so, you know, cache invalidation isn't
trivial. It's not trivial. And one of
the dramatic simplifications from a
distributed application standpoint of
hyperdia is that the hypermedia, there's
a term for it, hypermedia is the engine
of application state. And so you have a
representation of what was on the server
when you made the request, but that's
it. And so all the state is actually
encoded in the hypermedia. So I think
again I don't have a ton of experience
building super complicated single page
applications or JavaScript heavy
applications but I understand that
that's it can be tricky to you know what
do you do when the server gets out of
sync with the client and how do you
reconcile those things those are hard
problems that to an extent are
diminished when you go to a pure
hypermedia model and you just say look
the server is the source of truth and
you're going to make a request we're
going to respond with the new state of
the system and that's it. So there's a
big simplification from state management
when you adopt hypermedia. There are
disadvantages as well. So you have to
make a server roundtrip to indicate like
okay I've updated the state. What do
things look like? And that's in contrast
with a JavaScriptbased application where
you might update the UI like immediately
and then make a request and wait and
then that request will update the server
later. But I would point out in that
case that's called an optimistic update.
I would point out that when things go
wrong, that's good in on the happy path,
but it's bad on the sad path where maybe
that update couldn't occur for some
reason. So, an example I often give is
and because people complain, oh,
hypermedia based applications like I
can't buy a ticket on the subway because
the signal goes away or whatever. I say,
"Okay, sure." But at the same time, do
you really want to be told that you got
a ticket and then find out later on that
you didn't get a ticket? Because it
seems like the source of truth for
whether or not you got a ticket on that
thing or to that concert or whatever is
really on the server. And even if you
just cache that request and wait till
later, like what if your phone dies and
you think you've got a ticket or
whatever, it's all trade-offs. There are
certainly trade-offs associated with
hypermedia. think it does lean on the
server more heavily and on view
operations in particular. If every
single interaction causes a get request
and those get requests are slow then the
application is going to feel slower. On
the other hand, a hypermedi based
application doesn't require that every
click actually interacts with the
server. So a good example of that if
you're familiar with the details element
in HTML is a details element is it's
just a standard tag in HTML. If you
click on it, it'll expand a detail
section. And that's an example where an
interaction, a click, is not, even
though it's still hypermediabia based,
it's not interacting with a server
there. And so this idea that every
single interaction has to have some sort
of server request is not true. What is
true is if you update state, if you
update the state of the system, then
that should be done via a hypermedia
request with the server. It's kind of a
subtle distinction and it's one thing
that's a little frustrating when I talk
with people is that I really try to like
there are a bunch of trade-offs here.
You know, it's interesting because one
of the clear trade-offs is how much
interactivity you want and how much
consistency you want to trade off for
that, right? The example of the fully
SPA application where you optimistically
update the state, you could be wrong
only to be finding out about it much
later on in some other way, right? And
again going back to how this affects
performance for example you know where
is the performance shifting you know who
are you robbing to pay for who. Yeah
100% and I you know this is an area
where I do sometimes get a little
frustrated because my experience with
single page applications has not
particularly in the presence of like
unstable network connection has not been
uniformly amazing. You know I've seen
plenty of spinners in single page
applications in my life. So okay you can
put a spinner on a page as well. HTMX
has support for what are called request
indicators. You can put a spinner on a
request just as easily in the hypermedia
approach as you can in the single page
application approach. And so I feel like
there are tricks. Yes, if you need to be
off, if your application absolutely has
to work offline, then the hypermedia
approach probably isn't a great one for
it. But people have remarked and
actually a part of our essays section
has some examples of people that have
moved from React to HTMX and had much
faster applications with much lower
memory usage and so forth. And so I
think the simplicity, what makes
something fast being simple, right? More
complicated you make it, the slower it's
just inherently going to become. And so
the simplicity of the hypermedia model,
I think, helps in that regard. Okay.
What about browser support and
compatibility? I think you mentioned
earlier HTMX is trying to evolve HTTP of
sorts, right? Right. So, how should we
think about this? So, HTMX is
interesting because HTMX it's currently
in 2.0 and in the 1.0 line, we still
support Internet Explorer 11. And so
there was for a long time in the project
an almost sort of stubborn like we're
gonna support the old stuff because no
one else was doing it. But in 2.0 we
said okay look Microsoft declared
Internet Explorer dead. We'll stop doing
that and we'll simplify some of the
stuff simplify some of the
implementation hacks that we had to put
in to work around Internet Explorer
shortcomings. So at this point I would
say HTMX is it's very compatible. The
2.0 version is very compatible with the
vast majority of browsers that are out
there. On the other hand, when new
features come down from the browsers,
HTMX tends to introduce them but not
necessarily make them the default. And
so there's a conservatism to HTMX when
it comes to adopting new technologies
because and the reason for that is I
think the core idea of generalizing
hyperdia controls is that's what HTMX
does. People have tried to push HTMX in
like different directions. So, it needs
to handle this, it needs to handle that.
And I've really tried as much as I can,
and I haven't always been successful,
but I've tried to keep it really focused
in on just generalizing hypermedia
controls. So, I think that makes it a
more conservative with respect to like
the newer browser features. It makes it
more conservative in that regard. And
that probably lends itself towards
backwards compatibility. So, someone can
pick HTMX and be pretty confident that
almost any browser they're going to
encounter in the wild is going to work
with it. Can you give an example of one
of those things that's in high demand
but you're being cautious about it and
why? Well, I would say what's a good
example like view if you've heard of the
view transitions API which came out
about I think about a year ago in the
browsers briefly. Yeah. So view
transitions are a new API for basically
taking one UI and then transitioning it
as the name suggests into another UI.
And HTMX supports that. You can use
them. You can turn it on in HTMX, but
it's not available in Firefox. And so,
we don't use it by default. So, you have
to select to use it. Instead, HTMX uses
CSS transitions, which have been around
forever and are supported in all the
browsers. And there's a bunch of code,
which is kind of junky, I have to admit,
to make that work, to make CSS
transitions work because they don't work
easily unless you do some additional
work. So that's a trade-off that HTMX
would make is okay, let's support we
have this kind of okay, it's a little
crazy internally the way that it works.
But for the end user, it makes CSS
transitions work properly without them
having to think about it. Versus tearing
that out and saying, "Okay, use
transitions and start yelling at the
Firefox people to support it."
Interesting. looking at a couple of
advanced features. I'd like to
understand out ofbound updates, you
know, a bit more and what the security
implications are and what should be
developers think about and how. Yeah.
So, outofband swaps are an interesting
idea. I just sort of like came up with
them and they they've taken on a life of
their own. There's a lot of features in
HTMX that people either love or hate and
outofband swaps. I feel like a lot of
people love or hate HTMX. It's an
interesting psychological aspect of HTMX
is that there are a lot of people that
love it and there are a lot of people
that hate it. So not too many people
that are indifferent towards it. But
even within HTMX, there are features
that a lot of people love and a lot of
people hate. So I don't know what the
situation is. But out of band swaps,
what those are are in the normal sort of
functioning of HTMX, here's how a user
would use it. They'd have a button. They
put an attribute hx get for example
slashtodo slash one to get the first
to-do. And then they're going to have an
another attribute on that button that
says okay hx target equals say hash
output. And what that's saying is I want
you to take the result of the HTTP get
request to that URL and I want you to
put it into the element with the ID
output. That's what hash that's a CSS
selector if your listeners are familiar.
So that's what it's going to do. What
out of swaps let you do is when you make
that request and you go and you get some
content, you put it into that output
element on the page. They let you also
include another thing or many things as
many things as you want. Basically
additional elements that will be swapped
into based on their ID or and you can
use a CSS selector again for this. And
the stuff that will be updated is
elsewhere in the document. So you sort
of break this direct relationship
between the button, the request, and the
target, and you allow people to start
sending content to random places on the
UI. And what I like about that is that
it obviously increases what you can do
with a single request because you can
piggyback on these other updates with
the request. What I dislike about it is
that it makes it harder to understand
what the hell's happening because you've
got the main content coming down and
then this other content that's being
scrolled away in different parts of the
DOM. But it is a very powerful mechanism
and it lets people continue to use the
hypermedia approach in situations when
if they didn't have out of band swaps
they would probably feel pressure to
adopt a reactive approach in order to
update more than one place at the same
time. So to give you a sort of a
canonical example of when you would use
out of band swaps, if you want to
update, you know, like we just said, you
want to get a to-do and put it in some
element somewhere on your UI and at the
same time you want to flash a message to
the user. So you might send a flash
element in the response as an out of
band swap and that'll pop up and maybe
show for like 10 seconds or something
like that. That's sort of a canonical
usage of out of band swaps. So, it just
allows you to update more than one place
at the same time with a single HTTP
request. Almost like firing off a Go
routine to do something. Yeah. I don't
know. I I have to admit I don't know Go
routines. I don't know go that well. No.
No. I'm ashamed to admit I'm a Java
person. No. No. Sorry. Sorry. Or firing
off any Java thread and not worrying
about what it's doing. Yeah. It's What's
a good metaphor for it? Boy, it's hard.
It's like if you were sending a a
present to your aunt and you included a
bill for your uncle or something. I
don't know. I'm struggling with a good
metaphor here, but it's very useful and
I'm always, like I said, like I'm a
little uncomfortable with it because it
breaks the traditional model of a a
hypermedia control makes a request and
updates one thing. But it's proven
useful. So, can these autoban updates
trigger further updates like kind of
like a graph of updates? Yeah, they can.
And that gets at it the fact that HTMX
is event driven. So you can listen to
events and you know if something updates
you can issue another request. The
content that comes back can also inside
of it have additional HTMX code. So a
really basic use case for HTMX is you
have a div and that div has an hx get to
some URL on it and then the trigger is
load. And what that means is put this
div into the UI and then immediately
trigger another HTTP request to get the
inner content for it. And that
implements a pattern called lazy
loading, which can be really useful for
making a response fast, the initial
response fast, and then the thing that
takes longer. You know, you can have a
spinner and show the user, but the user
can interact with the content like sort
of right away. That's a a technique that
is very commonly used in HTMX
applications. So that's an example of
something you could do an out- ofband
swap with something that then has lazy
loading inside of it or infinite scroll
is another thing you can implement with
HTMX interesting whatever. So yes those
events can then trigger further requests
very easily. There's also a way to
actually trigger using HTTP headers to
actually trigger events on the DOM and
then you can listen for those and
trigger requests as well. It's a it
really is a Swiss army knife of
hypermedia. There's a lot of ways to
skin a cat. It is very unopinionated
which some people don't like because you
have to kind of figure things out
sometimes. How do I want to do it? Is
there a risk of this triggering infinite
updates or infinite triggers? And is
there anything you can do to kind of put
correctness checking in this somehow?
Yeah, there is for sure. One thing that
you'll often see when people first start
out with HTMX is they'll have a button
and then they'll click the button and
then they'll get back an entire web page
and now the entire web page is inside
the button. the button looks ridiculous.
So there are dangers. It's not a
strongly typed. Hypermedia is not
strongly typed and I think at some level
you just have to accept that there are
systems that are in place to do static
verification of not only HTMX but just
hypermedia links and forms which have to
an extent the same problem. I mean
you've probably been in an infinite
redirect loop at some point in your
life. But it fundamentally I think you
know you have to accept a little bit of
this is just you got to do it right. So
you know it's just software engineers
being software engineers. Yeah just got
to do it right. I want to jump into some
real world implementations success
stories that you heard of what
challenges they might have faced you
know what the impetus was are there
stories you want to share? Yeah, there's
like the story. The whole reason HDMX
started getting popular was because of a
talk that was given in I think 2022 at
Django Con Europe. So Django is a for
listeners that don't know is a web
framework very popular in the Python
world and an engineer at a company a
French company gave a talk about HTMX
called from React HTMX on a real world
SAS product. We did it and it's awesome
and as the name suggests they had a
really good experience with this. So
they're a news site. Uh it's context day
is the name of the company in France.
And they had a reactbased application
that they were building to show news
items with a some pretty sophisticated
filtering and so forth associated with
it. And they were in a bad spot. They
had a team of five, I think, or four,
but they had one front-end developer and
then sort of a lead developer and then
two back-end developers is if I'm if I'm
understanding correctly how their team
was laid out. and they were really
struggling. They were not making
progress. The application was pretty
slow. And the lead engineer decided,
hey, I'm gonna try HTMX. So, he tried to
use HTMX for it. And I have to say in
advance for listeners, I don't want to
oversell HTMX because their application
was ideal for HTMX. They're a mostly
text and images sort of orient. I mean,
that's media. this is hypermedia
wheelhouse, you know, and so them using
HTMX really was well suited for their
particular use case. But they did a
rewrite of their React app and it took
them two months. They had the same user
experience that they had with their
React application and they reduced their
codebase size by 67%. So twothirds of
their code went away. That went from
21,000 lines of code down to like 7,000
lines of code. So just a massive
reduction in complexity in the overall.
So there's no way you can lose that many
lines of code and not just have like a
like a huge weight lifting off your
chest. They reduced their JS
dependencies. So HTMX has no other
dependencies. You can use it without
even using Node package manager or
anything like that if you want. So they
reduced their JS dependencies from 255
dependencies to nine. They reduced their
build time for their web app from 40
seconds to 5 seconds. their first time
to interactive went from two to six
seconds down to 1 to two seconds. And
the way their application works is
people often click a link and go
directly to a particular deep what
sometimes people call deep links to a
particular page or URL in their site.
And so that first time interactive is
really important for them. That was a
very big deal to them. They also were
able to handle much larger data sets
because they were relying on the browser
to show a table or a list or whatever
instead of React which you know is
trying to synchronize a shadow DOM with
the normal DOM and just has a lot more
stuff going on. And so by just relying
on the browser they were able to show a
lot more data to their users which led
to a better user experience. And then
finally the last sort of bullet point
that we've got up on the website is they
reduced the memory usage of their
website by 40%. which is a big deal as
well from a performance standpoint. So
it's a very dramatic success with HTMX
and it is moving from React to HTMX. But
I want to temper that by saying their
application was very amendable to the
hypermedia model. And so what I think
that indicates is that there are a lot
of people think when you do a web app
you have to use React and that's not
true. there's a large class of web
applications that can be addressed very
effectively and often in a much simpler
way using the hypermedia approach. So
that's an example of a of a pretty big
success. Great. I mean for teams, you
know, looking to adopt HTMX and
obviously replicate the success of this
company, what would be some of the
migration strategies that can help them
be successful and avoid pitfalls? Yeah.
Well, the first thing I'd say is don't
switch to HTMX just because you heard me
talk about it. This is like if if React
is working for you, stick with what you
got. So, let's talk about non-technical
things to consider. First of all, if you
have an app that's working, like don't
change it. If you have an app that's not
working, okay, maybe now it's time to
start thinking about whether or not this
other approach will help. The reality
today, again, from a non-technical
standpoint, is that the standard
front-end technology is React. And if
you're concerned about hiring and you
want to make sure that you've got like a
good pipeline, a lot of people that know
the technology, then React is, you know,
no one ever got fired for using React at
this point. And HTMX is very simple to
learn. Most mid to senior developers,
even very junior developers, I think,
can pick it up pretty quickly. But it's
much less opinionated. And so depending
on what your backend is, you may have to
figure out the patterns that make sense
for your particular application. And so
there's a little bit more freedom. And
with freedom comes danger there. And
then unfamiliarity. And I hope that's
being addressed because HTMX is getting
more popular. HTMX won the JavaScript
rising stars for web frameworks last
year. So we actually finished ahead of
React and the number of stars on GitHub
for as much as that's worth, but it's a
big deal to me. So I think you it's
starting to get mind sharing. We have a
book called Hypermedia Systems. That's
at hypermedia.systems that's available
online for free to help people learn
that stuff. But I don't want to say, you
know, I don't want to there's danger
there. It's not the standard. And so
anytime you're not using the standard,
you're taking a little bit of a risk.
One advantage I think to teams is if the
team wants mainly to be full stack
developers instead of having this
front-end backend split, then HTMX can
be a really good choice because HTMX
moves the front-end generation to the
back end. And so your developers become
much more full stack. I often say I
think the most powerful HTMX developers
in the next few years are going to be
people that understand the web. So front
end type people, but who also know how
to use SQL because that's like the most
powerful technology on the back end. And
if you can tie those two things
together, which you kind of see them
trying to do with GraphQL, but they
can't quite do it because you just can't
give SQL to the front end. You just
can't do it. But if you're generating
your front end on the back end, you can
use SQL to do that. And so you can have
access to both these really powerful
tools. So I think that's another thing
that they note when they transitioned at
context day from React to HTMX is that
everyone on the team became full stack.
And there's a big advantage to that sort
of again not technical necessarily more
sociological which is that people they
tend to own features rather than parts
of features. So rather than a front-end
person fighting with a back-end person
about an API change, they just do what
they want. They're writing SQL. They
just change the SQL. You don't have
this, well, okay, we're going to get to
that change in two sprints and then two
sprints later like, oh, it's got to
slide another sprint. And at that point,
the front end person has forgotten about
the feature or whatever. You're much
more as an engineer in charge of a
feature from full stack from the front
end to the back end. And that can be a
much more efficient way to work. So
advantages, you know, there are
advantages and disadvantages. I do want
to stress that at this point, I tell
this to engineers too. Oh, should I
learn HTMX? And I say, well, if you want
a job, you should learn React because
React, React is the standard. But if you
have a job or if you have a project and
it's not going well in React or you want
to give another approach a try, then I
think HTMX makes a lot more sense. Fair
enough. You mentioned HTMX not being
opinionated means that there's a lot of
opinions. So what are some of the good
backend patterns or architectural
patterns you're seeing emerging that are
showing promise? Yeah, I think the old
patterns for good the the good old
patterns that we used to have. So I
programmed in Rails for a long time,
Ruby on Rails and there's a real strong
notion of models and views and
controllers and I think model view
controller is a really powerful way to
organize your software. So the ideas of
hypermedia and the uniform interface I
think are interesting. You kind of get
them by default. That's one of the nice
things about if you use hyperdia, if you
use HTML to be more concrete. I don't
know if you're familiar in the
2010s for a while it was like super
popular to argue about whether or not an
API was restful. Yes. Yes. I don't know
if you remember this, right? So everyone
he's like, "Ah, it's not restful. It's
it's level one, level two of the Richard
Muri whatever." And to me that was all
super alienating and it felt like kind
of puritanical like oh you didn't do
like oh structure. But the the nice
thing if you just use HTML, if you just
return HTML from the server, your API is
restful just by default almost like it's
very hard to make it not restful. So I
think that's one of the interesting
aspects about hypermedia is that it
takes a lot of these things they just
evaporate. Like how are we going to
synchronize backend and frontend state?
Well, we don't just goes away. Like
that's a whole layer of code that you
just toss you know. Now there's
obviously that whole layer of code is
doing something. So you lose something
there and that something that you lose
is that local cache of remote data and
maybe the optimistic updates and so
forth. And so there are trade-offs and I
think you have to make some trade-offs
when you're building things with
hyperdia. There are times when in many
applications you might want to do it one
way and you have to do it maybe not as
sexy, not as cool a way with hypermedia
and accept maybe an additional request
or maybe it's a little bit like you
click a button to save instead of things
updating automatically or whatever. But
I think if you're willing to do that, if
you're willing to make those tradeoffs,
then you can get a bunch of simplicity.
you can get back. You can drop a lot of
complexity and any software project as
everyone listening to this podcast knows
involves like there's a complexity
budget and at some point you're going to
go bankrupt with complexity and so and
so you need to be kind of frugal with
what we're going to spend our complexity
on. And so being able to give up and
just say not give up is maybe the wrong
term but to accept okay this isn't going
to be as cool as it might have been in
React but it's good enough. it does the
job. And because of I'm willing to make
that statement, I get back a tremendous
amount of complexity that I can then put
into say the backend code somewhere
where it's more effectively spent. Maybe
it doesn't matter if I can drag and drop
contacts in this UI. Although there are
you can do drag and drop in HTMX.
There's an example for that. But again,
like I think being willing to trade off
a little bit of front-end sizzle for
saving complexity can be a very good
trade-off in many cases. Would this be a
software engineering general problem or
react versus HTMX kind of decision
making thing right where can something
help you in advance know way this
complexity might be when picking between
HTMX and React yeah it's hard I think
and maybe it's an existential choice
right maybe you have to pick maybe you
have to pick to see the choice and I've
seen people say this and I can't say
they're wrong where they say why would I
pick HTMX when I might need React and
then if I you get into a position I need
React now I've got to rewrite it and I
would respond to those people in two
ways I would number one I would say
there's the engineering principle you
ain't going to need it right yagney and
so in general we've said before in
computer programming like you shouldn't
worry about the future too much like
obviously you have to make good
architectural decisions and the rest of
it again I do have an essay where I try
to lay out like here's the shape of an
app that's probably going to be pretty
good for HTMX The second thing that I'd
say to those people is that to get back
to what I was just saying, like
sometimes you can just say no, we're not
going to do that. I think front-end
people sometimes, and I don't blame
them, they're focused on the front end.
They really want to achieve a particular
user experience. But there are times, I
think, when you have to ask yourself, is
that user experience so much better than
just like say a stupid form of the save
button that it's worth all the
additional complexity to achieve it? And
sometimes that answer is yes, and
sometimes that answer is no. And if
you're willing to say no, then that
again expands the class of applications
that can be addressed effectively with
HTMX and can save your complexity budget
for other stuff. Third one is that you
can use HTMX in combination with another
technology, right? So HTMX is relatively
lightweight and not hard to figure out.
And I know people have used React or
Vue. For example, I think context day
actually uses a view for rich text
editor where they're coordinated where
it's like, you know, an interactive text
editor with two people editing the
document at the same time. And so they
said this is too crazy to do with HTMX.
And I agree 100% with that. So we're
going to use a view component to make
that happen. And I think that's
absolutely the right thing. That's
absolutely the right thing. So these
aren't mutually exclusive approaches
either. Now, the counter-argument to
that is like, okay, well, now I've got
two technologies that I have to
understand. And I agree with that. Like,
at some point, if you find yourself
using React all over the place and just,
you know, you're going to have to make a
decision. Okay, like maybe we'll just
drop HTMX then. So, it's all tradeoffs.
And I, unfortunately, I don't have a
crystal ball, so I can't even knowing a
project pretty well, I can't necessarily
say that HTMX is going to be 100% the
right choice at all times. I do think
it's the right choice in more situations
than most people suspect because I think
most people underestimate what you can
achieve with hypermedia and with HTMX at
this point. Going off from migrations
and corruption, right? How do you see
the developer experience side of HTMX? I
mean, given simplicity, you know, where
do you see the developer experience pain
points are, advantages are,
recommendations are? Yeah, there's only
12 attributes, 12 main attributes to
HTMX. So like how much developer
experience can you possibly have, right?
But the major idees are are supporting
it. There's language servers now for it
and it has, you know, some syntax in
some of those attributes. So but I think
the developer experience as it improves
isn't going to be an HTMX proper. HTMX
proper is not going to change very much
for the next, you know, hundred years, I
hope. But instead what it is is going to
be is it's going to be improvements in
server side code for managing
hypermedia. And so just as an example of
tools that I think help, there's a
concept again I I'm sorry to keep
referring people to the essays page, but
there's a a concept called template
fragments. So a common way to build
hypermedia systems in the past, right,
was to have templates. And so you'd have
some Java or whatever. Go has templates
in it if you're familiar with Go. but
Python, you know, whatever you're using.
And then you would have an HTML
template, which was sort of an HTML like
file with some special syntax in it for
doing loops or whatever. And one
technology that we've sort of advocated
people put in is a notion of template
fragments, which is the idea that you've
got a template and you want to be able
to mark a section of that template as
this is a piece of template that I want
to be able to render independent of the
enclosing template. That's really
helpful, I should say, for HTMX style
applications because what it lets you do
is have one template with all the stuff
in it and then you can sort of see
everything in one place, right? You
don't have to get into this world where
every single little snippet that you
want to update dynamically has to get
pulled out to some other template and
now you've got to navigate back and
forth and try and get into your head
what's going on. Instead, you can have
one template or fewer templates anyways
in the overall system and then use those
snippets within that bigger template to
respond to HTMX requests for a
particular update or whatever. And so
that's an example, I think, of a tool
that will improve the developer
experience for HTMX. And I'm happy to
say a lot of people have added this
functionality to their systems because
of that essay. So it'll improve the
developer experience in serverside
frameworks, but it's not really HTMX
itself that's changing. It's instead
thinking more like okay, how do we want
to do things on the server side to
produce hypermedia effectively? So
that's where I see developer experience
going and also for any listeners out
there, I wrote a book on HTMX called
hypermedia systems and it's pretty
philosophical, but it's sort of in
Python and it intentionally uses a very
simple web framework called Flask. But I
think because HTMX is unopinionated,
there's an opportunity for a bunch of
books that are more opinionated and are
like, here's how to use HTMX with X.
There's a book out on how to use HTMX
with Spring and Time Leaf. But
basically, if you're interested in
writing a book and you're passionate
about a particular back-end system, I
think there's an opportunity for pretty
much every for every application or, you
know, application server or web server
language pair to write a book on here's
how to use HTMX effectively with this
particular back-end tool. And that's a
weakness to an extent of HTMX. It's
unopinionated. It's a strength and a
weakness. So, it means anyone can use
it, but it also means that you're going
to have to figure it out. Like, how does
your system work? You know, be the
pioneer. Be the pioneer, you know, be
the change you want to see in the world.
There's a lot of good ideas. So, I
would, you know, highly recommend
people, even if they don't like Ruby, to
get familiar with Ruby on Rails because
there's a ton of really good ideas in
it. That's a system that I would say has
been really honed to a fine edge when it
comes to producing hyperdia. And so, I
think there's a lot of really great
ideas in there, Django as well. But
again, there's an opportunity there. But
it's also it's something that I think I
just you have to admit it limits the
HTMX ability to sort of take over in any
particular area. So HTMX has done really
well with Django developers. Has also
done very well with Go developers. And I
think that's because the Django people
already had everything they needed
except for a front-end system. Like
Django had everything except for that.
And then the Go people are so used to
just writing everything from scratch
because that's just the Go culture that
they were like, "Oh, cool. I can just
write everything from scratch like I
always do and do it my way." And so, you
know, I think HTMX sort of resonates
with those communities really strongly
because of that. I've had this
interaction before online where a
JavaScript developer who's used to
serverside JavaScript and all the like
generators and all the tools and you
just type you know npm run make my app
and it generates a thousand like they
they look at htmx and they're like where
is everything that's not where are the
batteries yeah it's not that's not the
HTMX thing I mean I can resonate that
coming from a go ecosystem looking at
the community in the future and
obviously the growth has been phenomenal
how has this ecosystem grown since you
first released it and what are the
trends you you're seeing in terms of the
adoption and community engagement? Well,
so it's grown really really rapidly
particularly since July of 2023 now. So
in July of 2023, two online influencers,
the primogen and also uh fireship dev.
Primagen is sort of has a daily show. He
does development and so forth. And then
fireship dev, he does these sort of 30
sec or I think it's 90 second I forget
it's some like three minutes as a very
quick and very well produced
introduction to some technical concept
and they both happened to cover HTMX.
Prim I would say more got into HTMX but
hardship dev covered it right at the
same time and that happened to be right
when we released our book which was dumb
luck because that book had actually I we
had been in contract with a publisher to
publish it and they had cancelled like
right at the end they had canceled it
and we were like oh man so we had gone
back and rewritten it. So the whole
timing was just extremely dumb luck but
it worked out so that there was a huge
boost in interest and you can see that
if you go look again the way I for
better or for worse I use GitHub stars
to think about the popularity of
something and there's definite elbow in
July of 2023 where it just started
shooting up. This is a serious podcast
and I have to admit my online behavior
can there were a lot of
antics and I enjoy that but I also I
can't necessarily recommend it for
everyone but that has turned out to be
very effective on social media for the
last year and a half and before that
maybe let's say the last two years in
getting attention and and so forth and I
actually I gave a talk at Big Sky
Software called a theory of open source
marketing where I sort of talk about my
experience of going through that and
just what happened like how did this
happen and some ideas so listeners can
go and check that out if they're
interested in in more on that but I
would say the HTMX the vibe is very
light-hearted and lightweight which is a
good thing and that's in general my
approach to live I don't take things
super seriously but at the same time I
do have a paper that was ACM published
paper on hypermedia controls and so
there's a mix of serious content and
joking content that I think has been
very effective for HTMX. Talking about
joking content, one of the criticisms of
HTMX is that HTMX is really a big ploy
by big HTML to take over uh you know
JavaScript frameworks. How would you
respond to that? Right? How would I not
know that's JavaScript is part of the
web? You know, I don't know. People have
they have a problem with proportion,
right? Everyone wants an eitheror and
they don't like talking in ans. Yes,
ans. There's an essay again. I'm sorry
to keep referring to it, but there's an
essay called hyperdia friendly
scripting. So, scripting is okay.
Scripting is okay in a hypermedivenriven
application. So, JavaScript is okay.
What's not okay or what makes something
less of a hypermediadriven application
is when you start having side state that
lives outside the DOM and is updated in
some other way and whatever. So I don't
think HTMX is anti- JavaScript. I gave a
talk at JS Nation this past November
called HTMX is pro JavaScript kind of
like saying how I feel like HTMX can be
interpreted as being pro JavaScript. And
the core message there is that HTMX
makes the amount of JavaScript you have
to write much smaller. That makes each
line of code of JavaScript more
valuable. And therefore JavaScript is
more valuable but you are writing less
of it in general if you're using HTMX.
But, you know, again, this I I love
these discussions. I love that like I
love the back and forth on Twitter is
where I usually spend most of my time.
But I have definitely heard criticisms
that the antics on social media might
hurt HTMX in the long run. I Yeah,
they're they're probably right, but at
this point, the graph is going up and to
the right. So, I don't know what to tell
people. And I I try to mix in the
serious content with the jokes. I think
you have to have both. I No, you got to
have both. I couldn't be a buffoon on
Twitter only. And I couldn't be an
academic only, but I try and mix the two
together. Seems, you know, it's time you
have a funny academic, right? Well,
humor, I mean, we all know it. Humor
works. Like, it's very effective, right?
Like, this has been known for a very
long. I said this on the primogen at one
point, like joking is no, what is it?
Humor is not a joke. Being funny is not
a joke. You gota you have to work at it
because it's a really useful skill. So,
but anyway, I don't want to I don't of
course as we get to the end, how can
developers get involved? I mean, beyond
just using it, how can they actually
help it grow? How can they help
contribute to it? The codebase itself is
pretty stable. So, I don't think direct
contributions to HTMX are going to be
like it's going to be hard to do like a
direct contribution, particularly a big
one. At this point, we're kind of in the
sanding phase of the library and so
we're, you know, we're just trying to
maybe sand down the rough edges. But I
have seen people come in and do testing
like more ad tests that have been really
effective and I appreciate that. It's
one of the most valuable things you can
probably do for software is add tests.
On the other hand, because HTMX is so
unopinionated, again, there's an
opportunity for writing books about HTMX
and a preferred backend, a preferred
technique that you've come across, but
also building up libraries in languages
that are designed to work with HTMX is
something that someone could do. There
are a bunch of those that are, you know,
but I think there's still a lot of
opportunity around that. So, I think
those are the major ways if you want to
contribute to it. But there's also, you
know, just reading the book if you have
a philosophical bent like understanding
hypermedia. There's always new ideas
that can come out of I I really like
this idea of going back and looking at
old systems. There's so much cool stuff
from like the 70s and 80s that people
have forgotten about. And I think going
back and looking at those old ideas, you
can find a lot of really good
inspiration. I've been on a kick. I've
been reading a bunch of Nicholas Worth
stuff from, you know, the 80s and 90s. I
don't want to say I don't agree with
him. That's like, you know, he's he's
operating at a level far beyond me, but
it's just really good to to see, you
know, someone really smart thinking
about things at the level that he is.
So, fair enough. Sounds good. Thank you.
Do you have any closing remarks? Nope.
htmx.org is the website. It's for
frontend hypermediadriven frontends.
There's an essays page essays if you're
interested in more philosophical stuff.
There's a lore page so essays if you
want to catch up on the social media
aspect of the whole thing and
hypermedia.systems is the book. There's
a hard copy, a soft copy of a few
different digital editions and then it's
you can read all the content online for
free on the website and also we've
uploaded the EPUB to libgen so you can
find it on libgen for free if you don't
want to buy it. So those are the main
places I would point people. I guess one
other one other website I should mention
just because some listeners might find
it funny is grbbrain.dev. So that's a
web page really that I put up with sort
of some observations about software
development that people might find funny
or infuriating or whatever. So thank
you. Thank you Garson for being on
software engineering radio. For our
listeners, you can find the links to
everything, you know, we discussed
today, including HTMX, its
documentation, community resources, as
well as examples in the show notes at
seenradio.net. Thank you very much for
listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by e
software magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
[Music]
seradio.slack.com. You can also email us
at
teamseradio.net. This and all other
episodes of SE Radio is licensed under
Creative Common License 2.5. Thanks for
listening.